[Music]
hey everyone this is an interview with
Thomas Bjorkman Thomas is a Swedish
businessman entrepreneur and philosopher
so Thomas recently released a book
called the Nordic secret looking at how
the Scandinavian countries went from
being the poorest in Europe the turn of
the century to being some of the
wealthiest and happiest at the end of
the century and he found that they
basically instituted a system of folk
high schools that a large proportion of
the population went to and what they
taught was effectively self-development
creating an inner compass and Thomas's
perspective is that something like that
is desperately needed right now to deal
with the pace of change but it's not
more information we need it's more
ability to navigate and more ability to
steer in this strange new world
so Thomas we've known each other quite a
long time you're a philosopher and
social entrepreneur we share a real
interest and passion for developmental
thinking systems change and also kind of
the deep stories of society you've
written about those in various books
including the world we create and for
full transparency you were also an early
investor in rebel wisdom and you wrote a
book about building and how that
transformed the Scandinavian Society I
think it's worth just recapping the the
basics of that cuz I think it's a really
great model for understanding how
different people have gone through these
major transitions in the past and
actually thrived as a result of it so
the book that I've written together with
my friend and colleague yeah the Danish
philosopher and writer Liana Anderson is
called the Nordic secret what we are
trying to uncover in the book is
political and and history of ideas of
the Scandinavian countries that is not
generally very well known not not even
in in Scandinavia and
[Music]
it's all about the fact that I think we
could say that the Nordic countries
manage this transition from a pre-modern
society into modernity better than any
other societies we know of now I'm the
first one to say that we are loosing a
little bit of this but what we did a
hundred years ago was actually
astonishing because at the end of the
1800s all the Nordic countries were
amongst the the poorest non democratic
agrarian societies in Europe at the end
of the 1800s 30% of the working
population in Sweden for example
emigrated mainly to the US because of
terrible living conditions people were
just like in Island at the same time
where were starving and then just a few
generations later all the Nordic
countries were at the top of the list of
the richest the happiest most stable
industrial democracies and the question
is what facilitated that transition and
of course there are many reasons for
that but one reason that has been mainly
forgotten in in history is the fact that
we had very visionary intellectuals and
politicians in all the Nordic countries
back then and they actually knew that in
times of rapid societal change and they
saw both industrialization and
urbanization coming so they knew that we
would have to prepare for rapid social
change so in these times of turbulence
it's just so natural for us humans to
want to have an outside authority to
hold on to
that could be a dogmatic religion or an
authoritarian leader but these
intellectuals at least in Sweden were
men mainly non-religious even atheistic
and they certainly did not want to be
authoritarian leaders they were firmly
committed to build democracy and they
knew that the only way to build
democracy was to build it from bottom up
so with today's language we could say
that what they wanted to do was that
they wanted to facilitate for enough
many people in the population
to create a critical mass of conscious
co-creators of modernity that actually
had come that far on their own inner
personal development that they have gone
from the state that we would today call
that we are operating from a socialized
mind where we are mainly dependent on
outside confirmation and guidance for
our for our values and direction to
actually internalize our values and find
our inner compass and be grounded enough
in ourselves not to be dependent on
outside Authority today we would say
that that is the shift in professor
Robert Kagan's language from a
socialized mind to a self authoring mind
and how they did this is quite
extraordinary so what they actually did
was that they created what perhaps could
best today be described as retreat
centers and they did this all over
Scandinavia and on a massive scale so at
the end of the 1800s year 1900 there
were a hundred retreat centers
established in Denmark alone
seventy-five in Norway and a hundred and
fifty in Sweden where young adults in
their early twenties later on with full
state such
I could spend six months in retreat with
the main aim of developing this self
authoring capacity to be able to become
conscious co-creators of modality and
when this was at its height almost
exactly 100 years ago then actually 10%
of each young generation had the
possibility to participate in in one of
these half year-long retreats and of
course that created some sort of
critical mass especially since these 10%
were not just sort of located in some
small elite in society in its own bubble
these 10% came from all different walks
of life many middle middle class but the
majority of the participants were
actually working class or had a farming
background and what sort of things were
they learning so and the thing about
personal development and you have
yourself David spoken many times on on
this channel about personal development
and how you cannot really learn personal
development that you have to go through
this sort of embodied experience either
planned in a retreat or something or
just what what is happening to you in in
life it might be that you hit difficult
circumstances in the middle of your life
a difficult divorce your parents died
you might have a bankruptcy or or
something like that and you really have
a need to start to to question your
fundamental assumptions so what they did
there was not so much learning it was
more trying to give the participants an
embodied experience so they're these
centers they were called fault high
schools they were
fairly small they had a living community
of about 40 50 60 participants were
often out in nature there was a lot of
reading was a lot of singing a lot of
experiencing nature but perhaps the most
important part was to create a safe
environment where you could actually
have authentic discussions about
anything in in in life so that that was
really the the methodology and I guess
that is not so different from what we
are doing today a personal development
retreats even if we do not today have
the luxury usually to be able to spend
six months in retreat it's always about
creating this sort of safe environment
where you can actually open up but then
get enough challenge of your your hidden
assumptions your root metaphors what you
take for granted to really start some
sort of on inner shift I should say say
that even though the focus and the aim
was on inner development there was also
a bit of learning so at the same time
you did learn about new technology so
that you should be able to embrace
modernity as it was coming and know that
we as humans can actually use technology
for good and bad and that we shouldn't
be afraid of technology but rather than
brace technology and also they the
participants were given the basic tools
for organizing civil society to you you
learned how to write an article perhaps
even how to start a small civil society
organization how to give a speech and
and things like that so if we would do
the same thing today it would be
personal development it would be
learning about artificial intelligence
and automation and social media and
things like that
it would also mean how do you do a
YouTube video how to argue for your case
and how do you make a video go viral on
social media and things like yeah like
that so it was really a broad and deep
program and one one thing of course one
could ask is so where did the these
ideas come from and the interesting
thing is that these ideas came from the
German idealist philosophers that wrote
in the beginning of the 1800s
so philosophers like gift Schiller
Hera de from Humboldt Hegel these
philosophers were all read in in German
original by by the intellectuals in
Sweden because back then German rostov
was the first foreign language and and
the academic language and of course
these philosophers they all reacted
against the enlightenment philosophers
view of our mind as a rational machine
so they said that no our mind is not a
rational machine or our mind is actually
a organic developing system and it's in
the mind is not just located in in our
brain our mind is embodied in the
totality of our bodies and embedded in
societal culture and under the
development throughout life and this
developmental process they gave the
German name building and they were quite
specific on how one could facilitate
this building process and the steps of
consciousness development that for
example Schiller and get wrote
explicitly about is very very similar to
what developmental psychologists today
at Harvard University and other places
our finding empirically that we as
humans are capable of going through
given they're in the right an
environment so one could say that the
the Nordic countries were were really
ahead of of all the time a hundred years
ago but as I said we are losing it a bit
now and we have actually in all this can
maybe in countries completely forgotten
about this because after the Second
World War we we changed world view and
we stopped reading the German
philosophers we turn to the anglo-saxon
world which returned to Oxford and
Cambridge and Harvard and there of
course it was the enlightenment
philosophers like Locke and discard with
again the tabula rasa the blank slate
and the mind as a rational machine that
was the model that was sort of
dominating analytical philosophy and and
other thinking so we wholeheartedly
imported that and contributed a bit of
our own
positivistic thinking there as well so
today we have two completely forgotten
about the importance of of inner
development and are only interested in
again the things that are our measure
measurable in a scientific or
positivistic perspective is there
anything that we we we missed so far
Thomas so I could just add there that I
don't see that the Nordic secret as a
blueprint for how we should do this
today but I certainly see it as a case
study showing that this interest that is
growing right now for understanding the
connection between our personal in a
development and societal change that
that is not a new idea that is an idea
that has actually been tested at large
scale in three countries a hundred years
ago
and it did actually work something we've
talked about before and I really value
your your perspective on is so we've had
conversations and we're part of networks
that talk about a more conscious society
and more developmental society and I am
interested in how much to those network
or how much do those interact with
policymakers with people who actually
have levers of power because you've been
in this in this game for a lot longer
than I have
how do you sense of where this broader
conversation is because I get a sense
sometimes there's a little bubble of
people talking to themselves about all
of these different models and some
academics and I wonder where it where
it's actually intersects with with the
the people who actually have kind of
agency and power in this current system
what's your sense of where the
conversation is at and what are the sort
of pressure points at the moment between
this kind of conversation and one that's
a bit more mainstream yeah I've been
thinking and writing about about this
for for at least 10 years and I ice were
very little happening out in mainstream
society so to say up until three years
ago but three years ago something
started to to happen and I think that
breaks it certainly in in in the UK
Trump in the US has made a lot of people
realize that we are in a in a deeper
shift than we might have thought and up
until three years ago in any of these
circles whether you talk about financial
circles or I'm engaged in in the think
tank Club Club of Rome or in political
circles
the main thinking there was something
along the line that it is a bumpy road
but we have democracy and we have the
market if we just give everything a
little bit of time and push this and
nudge it a little bit in in the right
direction a bit more environmental
direction then everything will sort
itself out I don't hear that at all any
any longer I think there are more and
more people in these circles are
starting to wake up to the fact that the
market at least in its present
implementation and democracy at least
again in its present implementation with
its high dependence and cohabitation
with with the commercial media and with
campaign finance that the present
implementation of the of democracy does
not expire and that we will have to
somehow look deeper into society than we
thought before so that's the good news
that the bad news is that depending on
how deep we believe that this shift is
it might be necessary for us to also
shift our world view not only shift the
system and here I think it could be
useful to go back to and build on what
you're done Hall was talking about again
during the rebel wisdom festival over
the weekend he was elaborating therefore
different levels of of systems shift or
systems change so so the first level he
was talking about was the shift
that we've seen in society during the
last say 50 years in in the Western
society and that can be the the
fundamental shift that has happened in
areas like civil rights or gay marriage
and things like that and these are
important shifts but they are not very
deep looked in perspective of of
humanity so if we call that level one
shift then level two would be something
like the shift during the Industrial
Revolution where the whole world system
more or less shifted but still it was
not a shift in world view we were still
sort of operating through that level to
shift with with the same worldview so
then level 3 as your nan pointed out but
that could be done the Enlightenment as
I mentioned before when we 250 years ago
say really both changed the system we
went from the feudal world system into a
market-based system and we went from a
religious dogmatic worldview in to a
scientific rational worldview and that
could sort of be a level-3 shift and but
then we haven't we have deeper levels so
a level for shift that could be and I
think Jordan was mentioning there was
the Roman Empire at the end of the Roman
Empire I think better might be to to
talk about the axial shift that both
younger vacant and your Dan Peterson has
been lecturing about how important that
shift was for Humanity when we
essentially left our hunter-gathering
anta gatherer society the society that
we have our genes have evolved to to be
fitted with instincts to navigate and to
through written language and through the
large religions create a new world view
but also social imaginary that made it
possible for us to live in cities with
tens of thousands of strangers and to
even form empires so a level four shift
would be the axial age shift 2500 years
ago and then to yordles four levels I
would want to add a fifth level because
Danny as master Berger has in in a few
interviews on on rebel wisdom been
talking about that he believes that the
shift that we are facing now could be on
the level of the shifting in evolution
in biological evolution when we went
from single-cell organisms to multiple
cell organisms and of course what change
depending on how deep do we think that
this change that we are facing is then
of course the demand on consciousness
consciousness development shift in the
collective imaginary and all of that
will be very very different but I think
that I agree with with Daniel that
humanity is now facing a possibly a
level-five shift I certainly believe
that we are right now facing one of
those phase shifts the main question for
me is how deep that shift might be I
believe that it is at least a level
three shift meaning that it is a shift
of of equal magnitude as the shift from
a medieval society to modern society the
shift during the Enlightenment that will
both mean that we were totally
have to rebuild our society but also at
the same time shift our worldview I
think that the deeper the shift we are
going through the deeper we have to look
into ourselves into society but also
back into history and that is why deep
history is becoming so popular
Yuval Harare sapiens or david christian
maps of times for example but also deep
psychological adji and deep sociology
the deeper the shift the deeper we have
to look into ourselves into society and
back into history and it will also
demand more of our inner capacities I
think we've talked many times over a
couple of years about a sort of a big
shift in culture and in society and
right now with with kovat and with this
sort of sense of a big systems change I
think we we all feel that something
something is happening it's something
you've put a lot of your energy and a
lot of your effort and a lot of your
your-your-your money as well into into
organizations that have been looking at
kind of the deep source code of society
and but I really want to hear from you
because I think you bring this really
interesting mix of philosophy and really
deep understanding with a very practical
understanding as well you're you're an
entrepreneur you're a businessman you're
not an academic who gets kind of lost in
abstractions so where is your sense of
where we're at right now in terms of
this shift well perhaps perhaps I
shouldn't start at the at the end and at
the beginning and talk a little bit
about a concept that I think this
discussion that is going on right now in
in the channel and and in the world
could could benefit from and that and
that is the
logical concept of collective
imaginaries just like you have done in
the channel you have looked at
psychology and you have looked at deep
psychology you have brought in the
concepts and perspectives of of union
psychology and that's really deep
psychology and also Jordan B Peterson
has been advocating our our need to go
beyond the more shallow everyday
psychology that has dominated academia
for the last perhaps 50 years and look
even deeper into ourselves in the same
way I think we need to also go back a
little bit in the history of sociology
and look into something that might be
called deep sociology and looking into
the very mr. practical foundation of our
society
so Charles Eisenstein recently wrote a
medium article where he argued that the
separate the myth of separation is
holding us right now in in a grip so the
book I wrote out of banking was called
the market myth so I also had the same
sort of answer as Charles that what is
holding society in a grip is actually a
myth and sociology and deep sociology is
actually studying how these deep myths
of society is creating what some
sociologists like the the very famous
social scientist Charles Taylor calls in
his book from I think it's 2004 the
modern social imaginaries is
a book called and so he gives us the
name the social imaginaries the
french-canadian sociologist gerard
Bouchard in his book social myths and
collective imaginaries from just a few
years ago he really connects this
concept on these deep fundamental
societal myths that every society has
whether the society is aware of it or
not with this concept of the collective
imaginary so then what is this
collective imaginary well it is
something that is even deeper than what
we usually mean by for example ideology
so ideology we are at least partially
aware of but these collective
imaginaries the major part of them we
are totally unaware of but but still
they form our society in an unconscious
way just like our own individual deep
unconscious is forming the way that we
act the social imaginaries are forming
the way a society acts and this can
sound very very abstract but I think it
might be clearer if I if I give an
example so a good example of a social
imaginary is actually money and if we
look at money from an individual
perspective in the modern world we are
equally one could argue that we as
individuals are equally dependent on air
or oxygen and on money to live in the in
the modern world we need air to breathe
and we need money to to survive but if
we look at
collective level there is a there is an
important difference between money and
oxygen because if we even if we
collected all humans and collectively
decided that we do not want to be
dependent on oxygen we couldn't do
anything about that natural dependence
but of course if we gathered all of
humanity or even everyone in a
nation-state and we decided that we
wanted to have another way of allocating
the goods in society then using money
then money could be gone tomorrow and
this sort of very fundamental difference
between concepts like natural concepts
like air and oxygen and socially
constructed things that is really the
the important learning from the concept
of collective imagined imaginaries and
as they are so different one could even
say that oxygen and money have different
ontologies to use a fancy word so they
are so fundamentally different and
because they are so fundamentally
different we also need different ways of
understanding them we need different
approaches to them and of course one of
the problems with the science of RV
economy is that one that science has for
the last hundred years been using
natural science as a model and I found
it much more useful as an financial
entrepreneur to understand the market
not as a natural phenomenon trying to
model it with natural science tool as
the neoclassical economic thinking
but rather look at the market as a
sociological phenomenon as something
that is socially constructed and as it
is socially constructed it can actually
be reconstructed by us humans and and
that is a very very fundamental insight
and is the is the idea of the social
imaginary more than just the market yeah
I mean this is everything
as I said it's deeper than is actually
captured in the terms like zeitgeist or
or or ideology it's more close to the
popular term the popular culture term
the matrix that comes much much closer
to what we are talking about in the
social imaginary is really to us like
water is to the fish we can't see it but
we are totally dependent on it so it's
it's really all our social myths it's
all our collective values
it's our root metaphors and we can't
usually see this but it is really when
the social imaginaries become
dysfunctional that we can start to
capture a glimpse of them so it's like
the the glitch in the matrix it's
through the glitch that we start to to
be aware of them and especially when
they are not serving our our interests
either as individuals or or collectively
when we sort of start to feel that there
is this strong force in society that we
don't know where it's coming from but
it's certainly not serving our interests
then it is probably probably the the
organizing the orchestrating power of
the collective imaginary
that we are feeling and when the stress
on the collective imaginary becomes too
large then like any again like any
self-organizing collecting
self-organizing complex system then we
have a phase shift then something quite
rapidly changes and the last time we had
such a fundamental shift in in the
matrix in the collective imaginary that
was during the Enlightenment when we
went from a dogmatic religious worldview
into a scientific rational worldview and
we left such a as ideas as for example
the Divine Right of Kings that really
nobody questioned during the Middle Ages
and we got new myths instead like the
market myth or the myth of separation
and and the number of these wrote myths
that we have that we cannot really see
but that something like the coalbed
crisis can start to make us conscious of
and especially this myth of the step of
separation I think the Kovach crisis has
made many of us wake up to to the fact
that we are much much more
interdependent then we we usually think
we we are so in that way the kovat
crisis could be sort of a awakening up
from from the collective imaginary that
we are living in also I should mention
that the collective imaginary is really
important not only does it inform our
sense making but it also shapes what
john de vega is calling the our salience
landscape so depending on our collective
imaginary different things becomes
important to us and we are using these
route metaphors and these rule
myths of the collective imaginary to
make sense of the world but but not only
does the collective imaginary inform our
sense making and our salience landscape
it also shapes our desire and that is
what Daniel smashing burger point
pointed out at the rebel wisdom festival
last weekend with a reference to energy
rod
he said that desire is mimetic meaning
that we do not even sort of own our own
desire our desire is dependent on our
relationships and our collective
imaginary so these things are super
important and again as they are to us
like water is to the fish it really
demands an effort from us to start to
see this collective imaginary but once
you have weight woken up to see it then
then you start to see it everywhere and
I could almost point at a point where I
in a more embodied way really became
aware of this collective imaginary and
that was actually when I a few years ago
together with my then 21 year old son
Alexander went to Burning Man and what
God got me interested in going to
Burning Man was that I had many friends
coming back from Burning Man pointing
out that they could not any longer
look at this default reality with the
same naive eyes because they're of
course at Burning Man you start from
scratch and you build a complete it
together your co-create a completely
different collective imaginary out in
the desert and you live in that
collective imaginary with other values
without any money and you actually see
that for yourself that you can shift the
collective imaginary
society is still functioning but in a
different way so then when you come back
to the default reality you you can't
really see the world with the same naive
eyes so I think it's good that more and
more people are waking up to to this
concept and that we are not only
rediscovering deep psychology but that
we are also a bit rediscovering deep
sociology you know there's a couple of
thoughts that come to mind or questions
that come to mind one of which is where
do you think we're at in terms of the
Kovach crisis and the other question is
do you think people are becoming more
aware of the the nature of a collective
imaginary because of the Cova crisis
because so many things we thought were
set in stone about the way we're living
have shifted on a daily basis and if so
what what relevance do you think that is
and do you think that's an opportunity
to change yeah so certainly I think that
the kovat crisis makes more people wake
up not not only to the myth of
separation but also starting to to see
the collective imaginary the problem
there is that we don't really have an
everyday or popular name for these
things that anthropologists and
sociologists have been talking about for
at least 50 years and that is why I am
trying to champion the collective
imaginary there the term of Gerard
Bouchard as a good name for this matrix
and I don't think that it's that we are
perhaps waking up and all of a sudden
that we see this collective imaginary
but we certainly get a feeling for that
it's something is something is wrong and
I think that that is one what again
Charles Eisenstein was
trying to convey in his medium article
that a lot of people feel that something
is wrong and then it's just so natural
for us humans to start to look at so why
do I feel this orchestrating power that
is making things happen in a direction
in in in society what is this and then
again it's just so natural for us humans
to then ascribe some human agency to
that and of course sometimes there is a
human agency behind of course but in
many many cases these orchestrating
power is actually the power of our
unconscious social imaginary acting and
making things happen and again when
these things seems to not be helpful
then of course you start to to question
this so at least the cope with crisis is
a starting point for bringing up the
issue of our collective imaginary and
how important it is to start to see it
but also to realize that it is a human
construct and that we we collectively
can change it and that we throughout
history collectively unconsciously most
of the time but sometimes consciously
have created it so now it's time for us
to be consciously aware of the
collective imaginary and actually take
responsibility for the collective
imaginary and again you were asking that
about post-modernism of course this is
actually a fundamentally postmodern
insight that we have in society these
power structures and that we need to to
look carefully into these power
structures where post-modernism goes
goes wrong sometimes at least in its
more extreme form that is when some post
modernist philosophers claim that
every aspect of the world is socially
constructed even for example every
single aspect of of gender is socially
constructed and that even air and oxygen
is socially constructed no of course not
you need to make a separation that and
understand that that sometimes you
actually have to deal with with nature
and the constraints of nature as a
starting point and for example we were
talking before about the fact that we
feel as individuals that we are equally
dependent on oxygen and money and that
we can actually not do anything about
oxygen or dependency on oxygen but we
can do anything we want about the fact
that we are dependent on money sometimes
I feel like we understand the world
exactly the opposite way that we somehow
believe that the planetary boundaries
are up for negotiation but that the
market forces we just have to obey obey
when of course it's it's completely the
opposite and and and there the more
extreme forms of postmodernist thinking
has has not been helpful you really need
to to understand that we as humans are
are living in actually three worlds and
this is something that many philosophers
throughout history has been pointing out
ever since Plato called popper certainly
Jurgen Habermas and Ken will breasts as
you mentioned they have all pointed out
that many others that we as humans we
actually live in three worlds at the
same time where one is the natural world
the world of oxygen and gravitation the
next one is our inner world the world of
dreams and fantasies and values and
meaning and purpose and then the third
world that is the collective
imaginary the socially constructed world
that has got its own ontology something
like between the natural world and and
our and our inner world and one of the
big problems with with the way that we
have throughout history understood our
human predicament has been that we have
during most times of history been
relying on one of these three
perspectives too heavily so for example
during the last hundreds hundreds of
years since the Enlightenment the
scientific worldview that is very strong
when it comes to investigating the the
natural world has so completely
dominated our understanding of of the
world that we are even trying as I said
before to understand the socially
constructed market as a natural
phenomenon and there of course post
post-modernism was a good critique of
our too much rely on us too much lying
on on on the scientific perspective of
the natural world but then again when
post modernist thinking goes too far
then you go wrong there as well and then
even in some spiritual traditions there
has been a focus on the inner world and
in some cases too much focus on the
inner world where you have perhaps the
idea that the only thing that really
matters and perhaps the only thing that
really exists is your inner experience
but I would say no that's not the case
Society is real and society is causing
real suffering so if you are only
concentrating on the inner world you are
missing important aspects of the world
so in our complex sense making today if
if I would give one recommendation that
would really be to try to start to see
the world from at least these three
different perspectives and understand
that we need different tools to
understand the natural aspects of the
human world the inner aspects of the
human world including our consciousness
and consciousness development our
potential for consciousness development
and then the socially constructed world
our collective imaginary and try to hold
all of those perspectives there at the
same time and in all of the shifts level
three or deeper we can really talk about
that we are in a world between worlds in
this shift and john de vega has pointed
out that that in shifts like that
we need new psycho technologies to be
able to develop new inner capacities so
i certainly think that that that is
something that we need to urgently look
into now at the same time as we are
prototyping and trying to support this
fundamental system shift that that is
going to be emergent so we will not be
able to plan it we will not be able to
manage this shift but we might be able
to facilitate this shift happening
because we shall remember that in these
systems shifts systems can go two ways
we can either have a step up in
complexity and in elegance of
organization or we can have a break down
so when we reach one of these
bifurcation points we can either have a
breakthrough or a breakdown and as many
as pointed out on your channel
civilizations tend to break down that's
the normal development for civilizations
the challenge right now is of course
that our civilization this time is is
global even when the Roman Empire
collapse that there were that was not a
global collapse that was a collapse of
part of the globe but if we have a
civilizational collapse now perhaps
involving in an environmental disaster
or a nuclear disaster or something then
then it's really the whole world so we
can't rely on the way that humanity has
sort of managed these transitions before
in a more or less trial and error manner
so this this time we have to somehow do
this consciously even if we cannot plan
it and even if we cannot even see what
the next civilization so some people
would call game B but there what that
implementation might actually look like
but we can facilitate it and again I
agree with John delay here that trying
and experimenting with different psycho
technologies that will help us develop
new capacities to to both see the world
but also to relate to ourselves relate
to each other
relate to society and relate to nature
in deeper ways that I think is a is at
least a requisite for a successful
transition so I think that in this
transition that we are facing now
that we don't know how deep it will be I
certainly think it will be a at least a
level 3 trend transition and that we
then again need to focus on inner
development developing the capacities to
understand and to handle the world and
to relate in in deeper and more complex
ways and that that is not just something
that a few people in some sort of
intellectual elite
need to do for this to shift to happen a
large part of
the population actually needs to be able
to hold this shift so Kristen is how can
we do that today and and there I want to
mention one initiative that my
foundation is involved with together
with the nauseum foundation in Sweden
called 29k 29k dot org which is a
digital platform where we are trying to
see if we can successfully use a digital
platform to replicate some of these
facilitation techniques and
interventions that we have been using at
the oak island that the a credit retreat
center and that has been used at retreat
centers like SL n fo for more than more
than 50 years if we can try to replicate
that in a digital environment that is of
course scalable in a completely
different way than these in real life
retreats are so I do think that real
deep change you do need the in real life
experience that you can certainly
increase the interest and also do some
work on on a digital platform we have to
see how how deep we will be able to to
go there so far the what we have been
trying that with for example these
sharing circles through video sharing
has actually proven to to work very very
well and we can see deep shifts
happening even on the level of what we
see sometimes at personal retreats so
yeah
it's still early but but it is it is
promising and just before I won't put
this on but is other the courses at 29 K
there at low cost or are they free no
sir so it's a 29k I should mention is a
nonprofit organization it's a
it's own foundation that we have founded
so 29k is completely free it's nonprofit
it is co-created and it is open source
and that is part of the dynamics of the
platform that we want to invite
researchers and practitioners from all
of the world to be able to upload
interventions and then to do research on
how these interventions are working on
different target audiences where people
are at different stages in in their in
their life and for people to feel
comfortable to share their data it is
comforting that we are a non-profit and
that we promise never to monetize any
data that we are collecting on the site
Thank You Thomas that was really great
thank you thank you very much David
rebel wisdom was set up to make sense of
the world at a deeper level than the
mainstream media it was built for these
times of crisis and change
which is why we want to do what we can
to meet the challenge of the times more
films and also for our rebel wisdom
members weekly sense-making calls with
our amazing interviewees and also we're
introducing the wisdom gym a place to
practice some of the skills that we've
talked about on the channel thanks for
watching and see you soon